Guide to the American Mission Movement Collection 1891-1953 MS 021 MS 021 MS 021
Cornwall Historical Society
American Mission Movement Collection
1891-1953
Cornwall Historical Society
MS 021
0.5 linear feet (1 box)
This collection pertains to Cornwall’s connections to the American Mission Movement.
Provenance
unknown
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
"This collection pertains to Cornwall’s connections to the American Mission Movement. While the community’s most famous involvement with missionary activity was related to the Foreign Mission School (1817-1826), this collection illustrates the continued missionary influences on Cornwall. Missionaries and prominent supporters of the mission movement are both represented in this collection.Items found in this collection relate to individuals who had a wide range of connections to Cornwall. Some, like Solomon Everest, W. Chester Ferris, Dwight M. Pratt, and Charlotte E. Baldwin were descended from prominent Cornwall families. Others taught schools in the community, such as Mary L. Phillips Thompson and Louise H. DeForest. Louise H. DeForest was also E.C. Starr’s niece, and her father J.H. DeForest, his brother-in-law.Several people represented in this collection attended school in Cornwall, namely Francis B. Barnett, James S. Dennis, and William L. Beard, and others preached for a time in the community, such as Charles N. Fitch, Elwell Mead, William H. Moore, and E.B. Sanford. Flavia Gardner moved to the community, and Masumi Hino spent one summer in Cornwall.Other individuals found in this collection have less tangible ties to the community. May Phillips’ work at the Lincoln Normal School in Marion, Alabama was of special interest to Cornwall’s Women’s Benevolent Society, and Jose A. Machado died in the community. The exact relation of Ebenezer Kingsley to Cornwall is unknown."
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains materials related to persons who had involvement with both the American Mission Movement and Cornwall, CT in some way during the period of 1891-1953.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged by series then chronologically within each series.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Missionaries
Miscellaneous
Cornwall (Conn.)--history.; Cornwall (Conn.); Correspondence; Articles; obituaries; Cornwall Historical Society; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
- Missionaries
  - Charlotte E. Baldwin’s A.B.C.F.M. certificate, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clipping about Rev. Francis B. Barnett’s mission trip to Liberia, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter sent by William L. Beard to E.C. Starr, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter sent from William L. Beard to John Calhoun, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter sent from William L. Beard to Conn. Congregational churches, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - William L. Beard publications, 24-Mar-1912 (Box 1, Folder 8-Jun)
  - Catalogue of Foochow College, William L. Beard, president, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Issue of the Foochow Messenger, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - James S. Dennis publications, 3-Mar-1908 (Box 1, Folder 16-Nov)
  - Correspondence between James S. Dennis and E.C. Starr, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - James S. Dennis newspaper photo, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Charlotte B. DeForest publications, 1913-1941 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - J.H. DeForest’s Japanese passport, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Louise H. DeForest publications, 1911-1913 (Box 1, Folder 23-27)
  - Obituary of Solomon Everest, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - W. Chester Ferris publications, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - C.N. Fitch publications, 1892-1897 (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
  - Obituary of Flavia B. Garner, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Article about house fire of Masumi Hino, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Biographical letter about Masumi Hino, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Issue of Talks and Thoughts journal of the Hampton Institute, edited by Ebenezer Kingsley, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Obituary of Jose A. Machado, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Elwell O. Mead publications, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - “The Churches Aided by the Missionary Society of Connecticut,” in The Home Missionary Vol.LXVII, No. 9, by William H. Moore, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Dwight M. Pratt publications, 1894-1903 (Box 1, Folder 41-42)
  - “Cooperative Advance in Home Missions,” in The American Missionary by E.B. Sanford, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - May L. Phillips publications, 1898-1917; , undated (Box 1, Folder 44-50)
  - Letter sent to E.C. Starr from May L. Phillips, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Letter sent to E.C. Starr about Mary Phillips Thompson, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Mary Phillips Thompson articles, 1927; , undated (Box 1, Folder 53-54)
- Miscellaneous
  - Annual reports of Litchfield County missionary societies, 185, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Newspaper clipping on “Christian Indians” of Conn., 1894 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Southern Workman Vol. 25 No. 12, with story on Stockbridge Tribe, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Newspaper story on early Conn. Missionaries, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Diamond Jubilee literature of the American Home Missionary Society, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Handwritten program for “Young People’s Mission Rally” in Cornwall, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - The Home Mission Monthly Vol 29, No. 24, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Notice for the annual meeting of the Women’s Foreign Missionary Societies of Litchfield County, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - “A Hand-Book on the Annexation of Hawaii,” by L.A. Thornton, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Newspaper article on annexation of Hawaii, undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - American Missionary Association booklet on North Carolina, undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Pamphlet, “Missionary Apportionment of the Litchfield Northwest Association of Congregational Churches", undated (Box 1, Folder 66)